Guide to the Maurice Parmelee Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Maurice Parmelee papers
1905-1967
MS 1744
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2.75
The papers consist of correspondence, writings, subject files, legal papers, personal papers, and photographs that document the life and career of Maurice Parmelee, eminent sociologist and economist. Correspondents include Louis Gaspar, Franklin H. Giddings, Russell Knutson, and H. L. Mencken. The completed manuscript of an unpublished biography comprises a particularly substantive portion of the papers.
Parmelee, Maurice, 1882-1969
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Judith Parmelee Hudson, 1999.
Arrangement
Arranged in four series:
I. Correspondence, 1910-1968.
II. Subject Files, 1950-1967.
III. Writings, 1905-1965.
IV. Personal Papers, Legal Papers, and Photographs, 1906-1963.
Biographical / Historical
Maurice Parmelee was born on October 20, 1882 in Istanbul, where his parents were Protestant missionaries. The family spent the first twelve years of Maurice's life in the eastern Mediterranean region before returning to the United States and settling in New York state. Parmelee attended finishing school at Oberlin College and received a B.A. in 1904 and an M.A. in 1908 in economics from Yale University and a Ph.D. from Columbia University in 1909. For two years following his graduation from Yale College, he worked through the University Settlement House as a "probation fellow." This position allowed him to closely observe the criminal justice system and led to many articles and books on criminology.
In the years leading up to World War I, Parmelee held academic appointments in the fields of economics and sociology at Syracuse University (summer 1909), University of Kansas (1909-1910), University of Missouri (1910-1913), College of the City of New York (1913-1914 and 1917-1918), and the University of Minnesota (1915-1916). In 1918 he served as a representative of the United States on the War Trade Board in London and he subsequently served the U.S. government as an economist for the Department of State in 1920 and as an economic consul in Berlin from 1920 to 1923.
In 1923, Parmelee resigned from the government and spent twelve years traveling widely, doing research, and writing on a number of topics including economic warfare, poverty, gymnosophy, sexuality, Bolshevism, fascism and world government. During this period, Parmelee published the books Blockade and Sea Power(1924), The New Gymnosophy(1927), Oriental and Occidental Culture, An Interpretation(1928), Bolshevism, Fascism, and the Liberal-Democratic State(1934), and Farewell to Poverty(1935).
Parmelee began working for the government again in 1935 briefly as an economist in the Agricultural Adjustment Administration in the Department of Agriculture. In 1938 he began a number of successive government positions as an economist working in the Bureau of Agricultural Economics of the Department of Agriculture (1938-1939), the Division of Monetary Economics of the Treasury Department (1939-1940), the Department of Interior (1940-1941), the Board of Economic Warfare (1941-1942), and the Railroad Retirement Board (1942-1952). While working for the Board of Economic Warfare, Parmelee was accused of subversion by Congressman Martin Dies. The accusation was based on the content of Parmelee's books on nudism and socialism and led to his dismissal from the Board. While working for the Railroad Retirement Board, Parmelee again came under scrutiny and was investigated by the Kerr Committee, a subcommittee of the House Appropriations Committee. He was not found guilty however, and he continued with the Retirement Board until his retirement in 1952. After retiring, Parmelee resumed his world travels and also finished a book he referred to as his "magnum opus," The History of Modern Culture. He married three times and had one daughter. Maurice Parmelee died in 1969.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence, writings, subject files, legal papers, personal papers, and photographs that document the life and career of Maurice Parmelee, eminent sociologist and economist. Correspondents include Louis Gaspar, Franklin H. Giddings, Russell Knutson, and H. L. Mencken. The completed manuscript of an unpublished biography comprises a particularly substantive portion of the papers.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Nudism; Sociologists; Sociology; Gaspar, Louis; Giddings, Franklin Henry, 1855-1931; Knutson, Russell; Mencken, H. L. (Henry Louis), 1880-1956; Parmelee, Maurice, 1882-1969
- Correspondence, 1910-1968
  Scope and Contents
  The series is arranged alphabetically by correspondent and includes substantive letters between Parmelee and Louis Gaspar, Franklin Giddings, Russell Knutson, and H. L. Mencken. The correspondence predominantly concerns Parmelee's publications and intellectual concerns. The series also holds some short letters from well known individuals such as Walter Lippmann, Eleanor Roosevelt, Upton Sinclair, and H. G. Wells. Also included are a small number of personal letters between Parmelee and his brother Julius, his wife Ruth, and his daughter Judith Hudson. Three folders of miscellaneous and unidentified correspondence are filed at the end of the listing.
  - Arnaldo, Solomon, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Booth, Harold, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Ellis, Albert, 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Farmer, W. W., 1962 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Gaspar, Louis, 1962-1968, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Giddings, Franklin H., 1927 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Haynes, Wallace, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Hoffman, Hallock, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Hudson, Judith [daughter], 1964 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Huntington, Henry, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Knutson, Russell, 1951-1964 (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
  - Lippmann, Walter, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Mencken, H. L. (Henry Louis), 1923-1927 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Miller, Justin, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Overstreet, Harry, 1928, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Parmelee, Julius [brother], 1960-1964 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Parmelee, Ruth [third wife], 1963-1967 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Philosophical Library, Inc., 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Rutgers University Press, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Scott, Howard, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Shugg, Roger W., 1958 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Sinclair, Upton, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Sisson, Albert F., 1961 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Usborne, Henry, 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Wells, H. G. (Herbert George), 1927 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Miscellaneous, 1910-1966, undated (Box 1, Folder 28-29)
  - Unidentified, 1961, 1963, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Subject Files, 1950-1967, undated
  Arranged alphabetically by name of organization, Subject files document organizations in which Parmelee participated. With the exception of the American Gymnosophical Society, the files concern Parmelee's involvement in groups and conferences advocating world government.
  - American Gymnosophical Society, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Japan Parliamentary Committee for World Federation. Conference of Non-members of the United Nations, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Toward World Democracy, 1955-1962 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - World Constitution Coordinating Committee, 1967, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - World Movement for World Federal Government, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Writings, 1905-1965, undated
  Articles, books, lectures, and reviews written about Parmelee's books comprise Writings. Researchers should consult the bibliography at the beginning of the series for a detailed listing of his most relevant work. The writings cover a wide variety of sociological, anthropological, political and economic topics including gymnosophy (nudism), poverty, criminology, capitalism, communism, fascism, and world government.
  Books include three unpublished manuscripts, the most significant of which is Parmelee's autobiography, entitled "Adventures in Many Lands: An Autobiographical Memoir." A draft of The History of Modern Culture, which contains many files that Parmelee labeled "Omitted Chapters," constitutes another significant portion of the series. One folder of lectures on a variety of topics and two folders of reviews of Parmelee's books complete the series.
  - Bibliography [books, articles, and reviews written between 1908 and 1954], undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Articles, 1905-1951, undated (Box 3, Folder 2-6)
  - Books
    - "Adventures in Many Lands: An Autobiographical Memoir" [unpublished]
      - Early draft, undated (Box 3, Folder 7-12)
      - Later draft, undated (Box 3, Folder 13-16)
    - "Association in the Animal World" [unpublished], undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - "Dynamic Cultural Evolution" [working title for The History of Modern Culture]1960
      - Book typescript (Box 4, Folder 18-30)
      - Omitted chapters (Box 5, Folder 31-45)
    - "The Heritage of Nudism" [unpublished], undated (Box 6, Folder 46)
    - Nudism in Modern Life, undated (Box 6, Folder 47)
    - The Play Function of Sex, undated (Box 6, Folder 48-50)
    - Pornography and Obscenity: A Handbook for Censors [two essays by D. H. Lawrence and Henry Miller, with an introduction by Maurice Parmelee] (Box 6, Folder 51)
    - "The Psychology of Clothing and Nudity" [unpublished], undated (Box 6, Folder 52)
    - Unidentified, undated (Box 6, Folder 53)
  - Lectures, 1954, 1965, undated (Box 6, Folder 54)
  - Reviews of Maurice Parmelee's books, 1909-1962, undated (Box 6, Folder 55-56)
- Personal Papers, Legal Papers, and Photographs, 1906-1963, undated
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material, the series is comprised of a variety of items relating to Parmelee's personal life and career. A small number of items in Government appointments discuss charges Parmelee faced of subversive activities during World War II. Approximately twenty-five glass slides depicting life in a nudist colony during the 1920s or 1930s are listed at the end of the series.
  - Announcements [flyers for speeches and books], 1936-1937, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Biographical clippings, 1960-1963 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Book contracts, 1923-1958, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Divorce papers, 1933 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Government appointments, 1940-1948 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Maurice Parmelee vs. The United States of America, United States Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia [re: censorship of Nudism in Modern Life] (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Passports and travel papers, 1906-1936 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Photographs
    - International Sociological Congress, 1937 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Portrait of Maurice Parmelee, 1931 (Box 7, Folder 9)
      - Travel
        - Italy, 1929 (Box 7, Folder 10-11)
        - Russia, 1928 (Box 7, Folder 12-13)
  - Slides [nudist camps], undated (Box 8)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Due to the physical nature of the material in box 8, staff supervision is required. Special handling note: Box 8, glass slides, needs notification by public services supervisor to the LSF manager for special handling during transport.